Wood Family Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
Wood Family Papers
1797 - 1874
The Wood family papers consist mainly of the legal and financial records of Ebenezer, Ephraim, and Amos W. Wood or Woodville, New York. Included are legal summonses, deeds, bonds, affadavits, land survey materials, accounts, and school records. Among the papers are Amos E. Wood's will and property records deeding his land to his six children; a letter by four different correspondence to Amos Wood while he was on a journey to Ohio in 1836; an 1818 contract for the construction of a schoolhouse, giving the location and dimensions and the amount paid to the carpenter, and a printed proclamation from President Van Buren not to participate in hostilities arising in Canada [1838].
3 boxes 0.63 linear feet
Wood Family
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
2012.049.0001
Collection is open to the public.
The Wood family is considered to one of the first families to settle in what is presently Jefferson County, New York. Amos Wood was the son of Ephraim Wood, who was one of the three brothers after whom the village of Woodville was named. The original name of the village was Wood’s Settlement, which was founded by Ebenezer, Jacob and Ephraim Wood in 1804, and at present lies in the township of Ellisburg.
Wood, Amos E., 1787-; Jefferson County [N.Y.]--History; Pioneers--New York [State]--Jefferson County; Pioneers--New York [State]--Ellisburg; Canada--History--Rebellion, 1837-1838; Ellisburg (N.Y.)--History; Woodville (N.Y.)--History; Portage County (OH); Frontier and pioneer life--New York (State)
The collection contains legal transactions, survey and land records, bookkeeping accounts and letters produced or received by the Wood family. The more significant pieces of the collection are the letters written by Amos when he visited Ohio in 1836, a contract, including buildling plans for a school house to be built [1818], and a printed proclamation from President Van Buren not to participate in hostilities arising in Canada [1838].
The papers were found, unarranged, in a wooden box in an attic in Woodville and given to Dr. Charles M. Snyder to be housed in Special Collections.
- 1. Legal Documents (Box-folder 01-01 to 01-19)
  Legal transactions made by members of the Wood family for people in the community (outside family members). Similar materials dealing with the same case have been left in original order.
- 2. Legal Documents-Wood (Box-folder 02-01 to 02-08)
  Legal transactions made by members of the Wood family with others outside of the family.
- 3. Land Survey Materials (Box-folder 03-01)
  Surveying and land records made for Wood family members by and with others outside of the family.
- 4. Financial Records (Box-folder 03-02 to 03-11)
  Bookkeeping accounts made by Wood family members for themselves and others outside of the family.
- 5. School District Reports (Box-folder 03-12 to 03-14)
  All records in the collection for School District no. 14.
- 6. Correspondence (Box-folder 03-15)
  One foldout letter including four separate letters to Amos E. Wood from E.C. Wood, R.M. Wood, Simeon T. Wood, Amos F. Wood, and H.D.S. (unidentified) on May 17, 1836.
- 7. Ephemera (Box-folder 03-16)
  All documents not able to be classified elsewhere in the collection:
  - Family Record of Ephraim Wood’s family on back of bookkeeping account made in 1802 by Amos E. Wood
  - Bookkeeping pamphlet, n.d.
    Unidentified records mentioning Enos Eastman, Abiah Jenkins, Luther Jenkins, Abram Farr, Esarlah Doan, Oliver Bachelaor (?), Amos E. Wood, Arhan Burnam, Ebenezer Wood, George Jenkins, James Botter, Samuel Truesdale, Levi Pierce, Orin A. Polly, Jerimiah Wood, Asa Cummins, George Harpham, Benjamin Wilcox, William Colvin, Caleb Tracy, Charlotte Phillips, Christopher Edmons, Jaboza Howard, John Varay, John Miner, and Asa Carpenter.
  - Certificate for Amos E. Wood of Participation in the War of 1812, June 1, 1814
    By Capt. Oliver Scott, Artillery.
  - Religious draft by unknown writer, February 12, 1814 or 1818
  - Masonic Membership Certificate of Amos E. Wood, 1819
  - List of supporters for burying ground near Ebenezer Wood’s property, November 7, 1822
  - Printed Proclamation by President Martin Van Buren, November 21, 1838
  - Printed poem “Strife of Tongues,” by Amos Eastman, 1859
  - Advertising pamphlet for “Dr. Tripps’ Blood Purifier”, 1870
  - Note on “Almira,”, n.d.
  - Agreement between D. Colvin and A.F. Wood (Amos E.’s son)